In this section, we're going to learn about what is a responsible artificial intelligence
or AI, and we're also going to learn about various tools and services that AWS provides
in this area. Now, let's start off with what's a formal definition of responsible AI.
So you can think of responsible AI as a set of principles that help guide the design,
development, deployment, and use of AI systems in a safe, trustworthy, and ethical way, and this
is critical here. So if I have to summarize this, what it essentially means is that you define
a set of guiding principles that help you design, build, and use AI applications in a safe,
trustworthy, and ethical way. Now, let's go ahead and take a look what these set of principles
are. AWS has defined eight key guiding principles within the spectrum of responsible AI.
So you can see all these eight principles that have been listed here. So what we'll do is we'll
go into each of these guiding principles, then take a real example of how and where they're used.
And then in the next lecture, we're going to look at some of the tools that AWS provides in
this space. So let's start with the first one, which is velocity and robustness.
So one of the biggest challenges while building applications on large language models
is, how do you control hallucinations? And what hallucination essentially means is when large language
models generate factually incorrect or fabricated response. So hallucination control is one of the
critical challenges in building responsible AI applications. So now let's take a real-world example.
Here is an article from CNN. You can see here Google recently launched a new AI chatbot tool
called as bird and bird is a large language model. And this chatbot was released
to the public in a highly televised live event. And during the event, one of the questions that
was posed to Baud was what new discoveries from James Webb Space Telescope can I tell my nine year
old. And the response of the Baud was JWST took the very first pictures of a planet outside of
our own solar system. But according to NASA, the first images were actually taken by European
Southern Observatory, very large telescope nearly two decades ago in 2004. So now here you can see
how this Baud large language model has generated factually incorrect response. So basically it has
hallucinated. And what were the consequences of this? The prices of alphabet, which is the parent
company of Google, lost 7.7% wiping $100 billion of its market value. Okay now with this example,
what is velocity and robustness focus on? So velocity and robustness focuses on achieving
correct outputs even with the unexpected or adversarial inputs or prompts. So that's the focus
of this first guiding principle. The second key responsible AI guiding principle is safety.
So earlier we learned about hallucination. The second key challenge while building
applications with large language models is toxicity control. So what is toxicity mean?
It means generation of content that is offensive, discriminatory or half.
So let's take a look at an example. So I went to this toxic degeneration dot ln a dot on.
And through this UI, it shows how various large language models can generate toxic content.
So in this case, I just took GPT2 and here is the prompt and the prompt is because men are
reasonable. And then I allowed it to do the completion of this sentence. And you can also select
the toxicity matrix, work safe toxic or where it toxic. And you can see the response it has
generated. So it says women are unreasonable. I cannot believe that they can judge the body I give
birth. So this is only toxic level. If I select where it toxic, it's going to generate highly
offensive and discriminatory content. So now this is where the second guiding principle from
responsible AI comes into picture. So safety focuses on how to prevent harmful system output
and misuse from the AI systems. Now let's take a look at the third principle which is
privacy and security. Sometimes there is a possibility that the model may leak private or
confidential data from the data that it has been trained on. And this could include PI data such
as your name, address, phone numbers and so on. Now let's take a look at an example. So here's
an example to this GPT2 large language model. We provide a prefix East status book status book and
the response it gave was it identified this person Peter and it provided its name, phone number,
email address and so on. And this was the data it had been trained on. So that's one aspect to it.
The other aspect is on the copyright infringement. So you might have heard about the ongoing case
between open AI, which is the parent company that made CHAD GPT and the GPT series. And the
actress Scarlett Johnson. So what open AI did was it copied the voice of Scarlett Johnson from one of
its famous movies, the Sky, without taking the prior permission. So obviously this is a complex
topic in the sense that say our foundation model generates a new poem or text or book or a certain
video. So who owns the copyright for the content that has been generated by the foundation model?
Is it the company that built the foundation model or say it's been trained on as in this case
Scarlett Johnson's voice. So does the artist own the copyright for the content generated by the
large language model or the company that built the foundation model. So all of these are still
areas of ongoing research. Okay. Now what does this guiding principle privacy and security focus on?
It focus on appropriately obtaining, using and protecting data and models. Okay. Now let's take a look
at the fourth principle, which is explainability. Let's now try and understand this through an example.
Let's say you applied for a credit card application and it was rejected, but you believe based
on your income status and other parameters that issued have been approved. So a lot of times the
and consumer might feel that the AI models considered for such applications like credit card
application, et cetera are considered as black boxes because we cannot understand what are the
basis for accepting or rejecting our loan or credit card application. So what you would
ideally want is a transparent loan and credit card approval process, which can explain clearly
to the and customer why his credit card or loan application was rejected. Now this is the focus
for the fourth guiding principle explainability, which aims at implementing techniques to ensure
decisions can be traced and explained. So ideally what you would do in this scenario is you would
clearly lay out all the factors that will impact the approval or rejection of say a credit
card application. And then say you have 10 different factors out of those 10, you can identify
say three or four key factors that have a much higher influence on your approval or rejection.
So we'll take a look at some of the tools later, which AWS provides for explainability,
but for now you just need to know that this principle focuses on explaining the decisions of
AI models. Now the fifth principle focuses on fairness or how do we ensure that there is no bias
in the decisions made by AI systems or the content generated by the AI systems. Now let's try
and understand this through an example. Let's say I pose a question to the large language model
and ask it to tell me about famous musicians. Now if our foundation model has no bias,
then it should generate a response that is diverse. It should include different gender,
skin colors, region and so on. It should not just include the names or images of people
with same gender identity or skin tone. So this is what the fairness principle focuses on.
It ensures that there is diversity within an AI response and each of the different groups,
whether gender, region and so on are equally represented in the response of the foundation models.
So sixth principle is transparency and this principle focuses on communicating
every possible information on how the model was trained, build, deployed and so on,
so that stakeholders can make informed choices about the use of AI system. Additionally,
it can also answer questions around if there are any known biases, ethical considerations,
whether it meets the regulatory standards of that region or not.
Now let's look at the seventh principle which is controllability and this principle focuses on
mechanisms to monitor and steer AI behavior. So you can define various mechanism through which
you can monitor your AI systems and this could include data-coloured tree monitoring while
you are training the model or the input prompts that you are sending to the model once it's been
deployed in the production. Then you can also look at the model performance post deployment
and we'll look at various tools that AWS provides to monitor and steer the AI behavior.
Then finally, last but not the least, we have the governance principle and it simply
looks at incorporating best practices into the AI supply chain and what that means is
whether you are a foundation model provider or you are deploying the foundational model
provided by third party. Across the ecosystem, we are looking at incorporating the current best
practices. Okay, hopefully now all these eight principles are clear to you but before we end this
lecture, I just wanted to show you a quick chart on what are some of the core enterprise concerns
and this is based on an AWS Commission IDC survey. Now if you can see here, AI ML business risks,
so top of the list is data privacy and we discussed about this earlier. Then you have the bias,
black box from the decision-making perspective, non-compliance with the regulatory standards and safety.
And finally, let's take a look at a chart. What are the potential negative business impacts?
And it could possibly be damage to brand reputation as we saw in case of the example of opening AI
versus Scarlett Johnson, reduced public trust, revenue loss as we saw in the use case of
board from Google regulatory backlash, customer privacy loss and hidden costs.
So that's pretty much it from this lecture. In the next lecture, we're going to look at various
AWS tools and services that focus on responsible AI. I hope you liked the lecture. Thank you.